Praise ye the LORD; for it is good to sing praises unto our God; for it is pleasant, and praise is comely. (Psalm 147:1)
When you wake up in the morning, is your first thought that I shall thank my Lord and Saviour now?
Why not?
Would there be any reason to give thanks?
Most definitely there is.
And it certainly there is, even if it doesn’t feel like it.
Well. Maybe you tell yourself then that no thanks and praise will come out of yourself feeling like just can't do that.
We Lutherans have a lot to say about that.
After all, we do not walk by emotions.
Of course, it is great and valuable that you feel and recognize your emotions correctly and don’t subscribe to any fakeness.
That's the way it should be.
But then, when it comes to praising God,
if you feel like that you are unable to praise Him
then you absolutely must praise Him.
Because that feeling is the surest sign that in reality you need it beyond measure.
There's a lot to thank about
Christ has died for you,
He has reconciled God with you.
You have the open heavens of grace.
What else can you ask for?
And in everyday life you get all what you actually need,
If all the people of the world history would be placed in a queue sorted by wealth,
you would easily be among the very rich.
There's a lot to thankful for. There is much reason to be grateful.
And because of that
no matter how you feel
there are still many reasons for giving thanks and praising God.
There is a reason why I say this, and why I want to highlight this.
Because in today's world
you might find yourself in a very difficult position because your conviction.
Being a Christian might mean that you may even be persecuted.
Now notice that the Christians of the first century rejoiced facing persecution.
We don't hope anything like that and by no means such should not be sought either.
But should it happen
that God gives it to you
you might temporarily find yourself in such a dark place of anguish,
that there hardly can be no other light than the Word of God
and no other joy than praising God.
You might guess that if you lead externally flawless life of a Christian,
and if you find yourself in such situation without looking for it,
it is most certain that God will help you there.
I want to read from the Book of Daniel, chapter three
something which might open the perspective of giving thanks and praising God
in a situation where thanks and praise are not the first things that come to mind.
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego,
in the greek translation Sedrach, Mishach, and Abdenagoo,
found themselves in a situation of publicly confessing their faith from which they could not retreat.
I read it according to the 1776 Finnish translation (in the 19th century revised language).
Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height was threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof six cubits: he set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon.
Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces,
to come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.
Then the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together unto the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up;
and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up.
Then the herald cried aloud, to you it is commanded, O peoples, nations, and languages,
that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, dulcimer, and all kinds of music,
ye fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath set up:
and whoso falleth not down and worshippeth shall the same hour be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.
Therefore at that time, when all the peoples heard the sound of the cornet,
flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and all kinds of music,
all the peoples, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshipped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.
Wherefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and brought accusation against the Jews.
They answered and said to Nebuchadnezzar the king,
O king, live for ever.
Thou, O king, hast made a decree,
that every man that shall hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of music,
shall fall down and worship the golden image:
and whoso falleth not down and worshippeth, shall be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.
There are certain Jews
whom thou hast appointed over the affairs of the province of Babylon,
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego;
these men, O king, have not regarded thee: they serve not thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.
Then Nebuchadnezzar in his rage and fury commanded to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego. Then they brought these men before the king.
Nebuchadnezzar answered and said unto them,
Is it of purpose, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, that ye serve not my god, nor worship the golden image which I have set up?
Now if ye be ready that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of music,
ye fall down and worship the image which I have made, well:
but if ye worship not, ye shall be cast the same hour into the midst of a burning fiery furnace; and who is that God that shall deliver you out of my hands?
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, answered and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we have no need to answer thee in this matter.
If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace; and he will deliver us out of thine hand, O king.
But if not, be it known unto thee, O king, that we will not serve thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.
Then was Nebuchadnezzar full of fury, and the form of his visage was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego: therefore he spake, and commanded that they should heat the furnace seven times more than it was wont to be heated.
And he commanded certain mighty men that were in is army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, and to cast them into the burning fiery furnace.
Then these men were bound in their hosen, their tunics, and their mantles, and their other garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.
Therefore because the king’s commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, the flame of the fire slew those men that took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego.
And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.
At this point the Bible differs from the very first Old Testament translation Septuagint.
The Septuagint has 64 verses in between,
among them the song in which the three men sing as they stand in the flame,
which is not included in our Bible.
The translation of that text can be found in the Bibles which include the Apocrypha.
The Book of Daniel is 97 verses in Septuagint, ours is 33 verses long.
The name of that Apocrypha, should anyone be interested is “The Song of the Three Holy Children”.
It resembles a lot like Psalm 148.
Which in fact is the reason it's fitting to read thru right now before we continue.
Praise ye the LORD. Praise ye the LORD from the heavens: praise him in the heights.
Praise ye him, all his angels: praise ye him, all his host.
Praise ye him, sun and moon; praise him, all ye stars of light.
Praise him, ye heavens of heavens, and ye waters that be above the heavens.
Let them praise the name of the LORD: for he commanded, and they were created.
He hath also stablished them for ever and ever: he hath made a decree which shall not pass away.
Praise the LORD from the earth, ye dragons, and all deeps:
Fire and hail, snow and vapour; stormy wind, fulfilling his word:
Mountains and all hills; fruitful trees and all cedars:
Beasts and all cattle; creeping things and flying fowl:
Kings of the earth and all peoples; princes and all judges of the earth:
Both young men and maidens; old men and children:
Let them praise the name of the LORD; for his name alone is exalted: his glory is above the earth and heaven.
And he hath lifted up the horn of his people, the praise of all his saints; even of the children of Israel, a people near unto him. Praise ye the LORD.
After that song the text returns back to Daniel 3:24 as we know it in our own Bibles.
It explains quite well why also in the most impossible situations
and why especially in those situations
there's reason to give thanks and praise God.
The Book of Daniel continues:
Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonied, and rose up in haste: he spake and said unto his counsellors, Did not we cast three men bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and said unto the king, True, O king.
He answered and said, Lo, I see four men loose, walking in the midst of the fire, and they have no hurt;
and the aspect of the fourth is like a son of the gods.
It is so that thank and praise are in a sense joining an exulting and joyful heavenly worship.
The less you feel that you could actually give thanks
the bigger reason there is to give thanks.
And when you do so.
You'll soon recognize that
figuratively speaking the surrounding fires cool down
and you will find that there is that same fourth man, Christ, Son of God, with you
just where you are.
And if that's not enough reason to thank and praise God when you don’t feel like it, then no reason will do.
Additionally proper thanksgiving and praise always give honor to God.
It skyjacks you away from what you are.
It looks only to Christ,
to the giver of all things good, to the author and the finisher of our faith.
For that reason, if you aren't sure
on how to give thanks and praise properly
look no further than the end of the book of Psalms. There are many great chapters
which you are able to read and pray aloud
— one of the forms of praying is thanksgiving —
and if you are unable to find the correct words, then there are no better words
than to pray according to the Word of God.
Psalms 145, 146, 147, 148 all the way to the end of the book.
They all are great. If you don't know how to give thanks and praise to God,
begin with those.
Whatever the reason would be why giving thanks and praise feels difficult,
praising will also help a lot.
The Psalm 147:3 says:
He, that is our LORD, God, Christ
He healeth the broken in heart,
and bindeth up their wounds.
So when you start your day
if you find it hard feeling thankful,
then pray using those words of the Psalms.
O GIVE thanks unto the LORD;
for he is good:
for his mercy endureth for ever.
Thus says Psalm 118:1
and that's also what the three men sang as they stood in the flames of the fiery furnace.
Stay protected in our good and merciful Savior Lord Jesus Christ
and remain in His peace.
Scripture taken from The Holy Bible (1885), English Revised Version.